# 大家好 現在下雨啦 天氣好冷哦
Hi everyone! It's raining now and it's really cold.
# 我們去看一下那個竹鼠 看下會不會感冒
Let's have a look at the bamboo rats, and see if they will get a cold.
# 你看 這是大胖和小胖
Look! They're Big Fatty and Small Fatty.
# 它們在同一個被窩裡面
They're in the same blanket.
# 大胖都到現在都沒懷孕
Big Fatty is still not yet pregnant.
# 怎麼搞的
How can it be?
# 你看
Look!
# 這個是 小胖
This is, Small Fatty.
# 小胖
Small Fatty!
# 好暖啊 暖手寶
It's so warm, like a heating pad
# 挺舒服的
It feels rather good.
# 你看 它現在 不肯了 哎呦 你還抓我 這樣不行
Look! It's now, it doesn't like it. Ayo! You scratched me. This will be problem.
# 這小狗跑到裡面去啦
The puppies have run inside.
# 兩條小狗 路過來啦
The two puppies, they're coming now.
# 出去出去出去
Get out, get out, get out!
# 這裡不適合你們待
It's not a place for you guys.
# 快點回去哦
Get out! Hurry up!
# 這個就是大胖 它指甲好利哦
This is Big Fatty. Her finger nails are really sharp.
# 你看 大胖
Look! Big Fatty!
# 是不是流鼻涕了
Are you having a running nose?
# 應該不像啊
No, I don't think so.
# 沒事 忍一忍 (註︰忍甚麼？忍著不在他面對流？)
It's okay. Hang in there.
# 誒呦 抓我一下
Ayo! She scratched me.
# 那兩條小狗不知道幹嘛 我去看一下
What happened to those two puppies? Let me go and have a look.
# 吃竹子
They're eating bamboo.
# 你有那麼餓嗎
Are you really that hungry?
# 你看這個 我看它吃甚麼
Look at this puppy! Let me see what it is eating.
# 走開走開走開
Go 'way, go 'way, go 'way!
# 你看 吃象草
Look! It's eating elephant grass!
# 是不是我弟沒餵你們
Haven't my brother fed you?
# 那麼餓
You look like starving.
# 怎麼竹子象草都要吃啦
Why do you need to eat bamboo and elephant grass?
# 不要那麼調皮
Don't be that naughty!
# 要不要石頭 給你吃石頭
You want the stone? You can eat the stone.
# 家裡都有飯吃 它不吃
They have proper meals at home. But they're not eating.
# 跑到這裡來吃零食
And they come here for snacks.
# 你看 那石頭它都喜歡去咬
Look! It enjoys chewing it so much. Just a stone.
# 走 出去出去出去 別在這裡咯
Go! Get out, get out, get out! Don't stay here!
# 叫不聽它們
They're not listening.
# 你看 這些就是斷奶了差不多一個月
Look! These are the baby rats which have been weaned for,
# 一個月的小鼠崽
almost a month, for a month.
# 肚子都白的這個
This one has a white belly.
# 它媽的肚子也是白的
Its mother also has a white belly.
# 它那無處安放的小手
Its little hands have not good place to land on.
# 抓我啊 抓我啊
Catch me! Catch me!
# 好暖啊
It's so warm.
# 給我 做暖手寶
I wanna take it, as a heating pad.
# 好暖啊
It's so warm.
# 它身上好暖 哎呦
It's body is really warm. Ayo!
# 哎呀 屙屎啦 (註︰原字幕沒有)
Aya! It poops.
# 壞蛋
Naughty!
# 抓的時候這小的就直接可以這樣
That's how I take it when it's still small.
# 揪 抓起來的時候
Grab and take
# 因為它太小啦 力氣沒那麼大
Cuz it's too small. So it's not that strong.
# 它這爪子很利的哦
Its claws are really sharp.
# 這個肚皮上有點白的
Its belly is a bit white.
# 是不是小白
Is it from Whitey?
# 它應該是小白的後代
It must be Whitey's offspring.
# 聽話 不許動
Be a good rat! Don't move!
# 再動我就把你賣了
Otherwise I'll have you sold.
# 現在乖啦
Much better now.
# 說完它又這樣子了
It's naughty again.
# 聽話
Behave!
# 不聽話我把你烤啦
I'll have you roasted if you don't.
# 沒事 還那麼小
No worries. You're still small.
# 現在就一點點
Just a tiny little rat.
# 哎呦
Ayo!
# 剛好撞到那個泥上
It crashed onto the mud,
# 接到它的屎里面
into its poo.
# 沒事
No worries.
# 現在天冷啦 它們都
Now it's winter. They're all,
# 窩在一起
clinging together,
# 互相取暖
to stay warm.
# 你看這個 這個好大
Look at this one. It's so big.
# 好大啊這個
It's really big.
# 這是這樣就可以啊
It's already good enough.
# 哇 那麼小你想咬我啊
Wa! You wanna bite me? You're still that tiny.
# 我去看一下西西和瓜瓜 西西在那邊
Let me have a look at Xi Xi and Gua Gua. Xi Xi is over there.
# 它在
She's now under,
# 產後恢復
postpartum care.
# 這個西西
This is Xi Xi.
# 它害怕
She's scared,
# 一直在退
and is stepping back.
# 你看 這個西西
Look at Xi Xi.
# 西西
Xi Xi
# 現在都長 長胖了一點點
She's a bit, a bit heavier now,
# 帶兩個崽
nursing two babies.
# 別抓我的手哦
Don't scratch my hands!
# 下次給 小白
Next time, Whitey.
# 給小白配種
Let Whitey mate with her.
# 我再去看一下瓜瓜 瓜瓜在 在
Now let me take a look at Gua Gua. Gua Gua is er... is er...
# 我也不知道哪個是瓜瓜了
I don't know which one is Gua Gua anymore.
# 這附近這一帶
He should be somewhere here,
# 不知道是哪個
one of these.
# 這個 像不像瓜瓜 這個
This one... Does it look like Gua Gua? This one...
# 那是候瓜瓜這裡有點毛黃的 好像就這個
I remember that Gua Gua had some brown hair here. It should be Gua Gua.
# 誒
Ey?
# 這個是母的哦
It's female!
# 不好意思
I'm sorry.
# 看錯了
My mistake
# 我也不知道哪個啦 反正這附近一帶
I don't know which one. He's somewhere here anyway.
# 管它 反正還在
Who cares? He's still here anyway.
# 我又沒把它吃啦
I haven't eaten him.
# 你看 這個 小白 小白都黑啦 小白
Look! This is Whitey. Whitey is now getting black, Whitey.
# 老了
He's old.
# 你看
Look!
# 這個小白 昨 前兩天跟人家打架
Whitey got into a fight yeste...a couple of days ago,
# 打了一身都是傷
and was covered by wounds.
# 前一 前一個禮拜了
It was, it was a week ago.
# 被我醫好啦
I cured him.
# 好多那些 傷口 你看
There are, I mean, many wounds, look!
# 這傷口都好啦 結疤啦
The wounds are healed, only the scabs remain.
# 沒問題啦
He's fine now.
# 小白
Whitey!
# 要好好的活下去哦
Promise me to have a nice life, Okay?
# 你們兩個打架啊
You two are having a fight, aren't you?
# 我一來它就不打啦
They stop once I arrive.
# 是不是你 以為你大個一點你就欺負人家
Is that you? You bully your cellmate cuz you think you are bulky, eh?
# 這個好像是母的
This one seems to be female.
# 這是母的
Yup, female.
# 咬它
Bite it!
# 來到它又不打了
They don't fight when I'm here.
# 剛剛 看到它打架 我就過來看
I just, I just saw them fighting. That's why I came and have a look.
# 你看這個小粉 哎呀小粉 過來過來過來
Look at Fanny. Aya Fanny! Come here, come here, come here!
# 提著這裡 誒 好像有點黑黑的
I grab here. Eh? It seems to be a bit black.
# 那麼兇幹嘛
How come you are that fierce?
# 抓來看一來 檢查一下你身體
I'm just taking you to have look and do a body check.
# 檢查一下你身體好不好
Can I do a body check for you?
# 你看 現在
Look! He's now,
# 結實的[SIC]很了
really strong.
# 很壯哦
So fit
# 肚子怎麼那麼大
Why is the belly that big?
# 可以
He passes.
# 健健康康
Super healthy
# 沒啥問題
Free from problems
# 這個 很乖的哦 這隻是從兄 從兄弟家抓回來的
This is, really nice. It's taken from my budd, my buddy.
# 兄弟的竹鼠就是好 都不咬人
My buddies' bamboo rats are always nice. They never bite.
# 很好玩的哦
It's really fun.
# 它咬不到 想咬我它咬不到
It can't bite me. It wants to bite me but it can't.
# 不胖也不瘦
It's not too fat, not too skinny.
# 身村剛剛好
Perfect build.
# 這樣的竹鼠拿去做紅燒的話
If I make a braised dish with this kind of bamboo rats,
# 很好吃的哦
it would taste really nice.
# 下次你感冒啊
Remember to let me know,
# 發燒啦記得叫我啊
when you have a cold or a fever.
# 我幫你醫
I'll cure you.
# 你看 這個在吃竹子
Look! This one is eating bamboo.
# 一說它吃竹子就馬上不吃了
It stops immediately once I talk about it.
# 吃竹子是好事哦 不能不吃的
Eating bamboo is good for you. You must eat.
# 胖的你看它的 差點眼睛都看不到了
It's so fat that, look, that I can hardly see its eyes.
# 你看這個 很胖的哦 它肚子都很大了
Look that this rat! It's so fat. It has a really large belly.
# 但是這個是公的
But it's male.
# 過兩天給它發老婆
I'll send it a wife in a couple of days.
# 這是兄弟家的竹鼠 這個
It's my buddy's bamboo rat.
# 這
It's,
# 上次我去兄弟家拿回來的
it was taken from my buddy last time.
# 公的
It's male.
# 借一點兄弟的公的回來
We borrowed some male rats from our buddy.
# 還可以哦
Not bad, right?
# 這種是銀星竹鼠
This is a hoary bamboo rat.
# 它那毛尖是白的
The tip of the hair is white.
# 我們這邊是
And ours,
# 毛尖是黑的
the tip of the hair is black,
# 或者 偏黃
or, a bit brown.
# 它就是
They are,
# 中華 竹鼠
Chinese bamboo rats.
# 屎都嚇出來了
I scared the poop out of it.
# 這小的 多放一點它比較那個
These are the small ones. I put more in a cell, so that they, you know,
# 比較 比較暖一點
they feel warmer.
# 這個是懷孕的 所以把它單獨放在一個池子裡面
This is pregnant. So I put it in a single cell alone.
# 現在都 比較老了這種
It's already a bit old.
# 毛比較黃一點
Its hair is a bit brown.
# 你看 這個生了差不多 差不多十七八天吧
Look! These are around, around seventeen or eighteen days old.
# 那麼小一點點
They're so tiny.
# 你看這個 是母鼠
Look at this one. It's their mom.
# 剛才看了一下小豬哇
I've just taken a look at the piggies.
# 它笨得要死 它們
They're damn stupid.
# 有那個窩它們不去
There's a pigsty but they're not staying there.
# 有那個棚子它們也不鑽進去
There's a shed but they're not going in.
# 就在那外面淋雨
They just stay outside, in the rain.
# 哎 真的是氣死人啦
Ay! Damn it!
# 浪費我的稻草
They're wasting my straw.
# 給它做一個窩
I'll make them a lair.
# 你看 這些豬笨不笨
Look! Aren't the pigs stupid?
# 那不是有棚嗎
Can't you see the sheds?
# 那兩個棚都在那裡 它都不住
Both sheds are over there. But they're not staying there.
# 就住在這裡 淋雨
They're just staying here, in the rain.
# 特別是
Especially,
# 這個公豬
the boar,
# 公豬笨得要死
the boar is really damn stupid.
# 浪費我的稻草
It wastes my straw.
# 給你墊一下
You can sleep on it.
# 現在豬崽子好胖啊
The piglets are really heavy now.
# 今天天氣好冷啊
It's very cold today.
# 都
er em...
# 才五六度
It's only five or six degrees.
# 五六度
Five or six
# 你看 這小豬
Look! This piglet,
# 有點冷
is feeling a bit cold.
# 揍它
Let me beat it!
# 那麼不聽話
Naughty!
# 給你們給一下窩 暖和一點
So I made you a lair, to keep you warm.
# 怕你們
I don't wanna see you,
# 在這裡 淋雨
staying in the rain here
# 那個棚里它們也不去
They're not going into the sheds,
# 這裡也不去 那裡也不去
neither here nor there.
# 這樣怎麼行啊
This will be a problem.
# 晚上著涼啦
You may get a cold at night.
# 著涼的下果
I bet you know the consa,
# 下場你們知道吧
the consequence of getting cold, don't you?
# 好冷啊 現在
It's really cold now
# 現在快下雨啦
It will soon be raining.
# 先回去啦
We need to head back.
# 不管它們啦
Let's leave them alone.
# 我做的只能這樣子啦
That's all what I can do.
# 反正那棚也有 窩也有
You still have a shed and a pigsty.
# 你們要到這裡
But you decide to stay here.
# 感冒了就要
If you get a cold,
# 叫我
call me!
# 我幫你們看
I'll be there.